Lionel Andres Messi
莱昂内尔·安德烈斯·梅西
Hailed by football enthusiasts, analysts, and even fellow professionals as the greatest footballer to ever play the sport.
被足球爱好者、分析师，甚至同行职业球员誉为有史以来最伟大的足球运动员。
【Spanish】
有人告诉我："我看过贝利踢球，我看过马拉多纳踢球，我也可以说，我看过里奥·梅西踢球。"There are people who tell me, I saw Pelé play, I saw Maradona play, I can say that I saw Leo Messi play.
He doesn't have the ball. It's unbelievable the character, how he plays, how he works for the team. He's one of the gods of football.
他脚下没有球的时候也是如此出色。他的品格、踢球方式以及为球队付出的精神都令人难以置信。他就是足球界的传奇人物之一。
He has achieved a groundbreaking six Ballon d'Or awards, six European Golden Shoes, and holds records for the most goals and assists in La Liga history.
他获得了创纪录的六座金球奖、六座欧洲金靴奖，并保持着西甲历史进球数和助攻数最多的纪录。
Diagnosed with a medical condition at just 11 years old that could have derailed his career before it even started, Messi defied expectations and stunned the world with his extraordinary footballing talent.
梅西在年仅11岁时便被诊断出患有一种可能让他的职业生涯尚未开始就夭折的疾病，但他打破了所有人的预期，并凭借非凡的足球天赋震惊了世界。
Statistics and history go out the window, the way he's playing.
按照他现在这种踢法，数据和历史纪录都显得无关紧要了。
Experience the journey of one of football's most legendary figures, and delve into the story of Argentina's footballing icon.
一起踏上足球史上最具传奇色彩人物之一的旅程，深入了解这位阿根廷足球偶像的故事。
【Spanish】
我成长了，也学到了很多，现在我仍然努力不断丰富自己的足球水平。I grew up, I learned a lot, and now I try to keep adding things to my football.
This is the mesmerizing tale of Lionel Messi.
这就是莱昂内尔·梅西令人着迷的传奇故事。
Born on June 24, 1987, Lionel Andres Messi grew up in a city that breathes football, Rosario, the largest city in Santa Fe. Messi was raised by his father, a steel factory manager and part-time football coach, and his mother, who worked in a magnet manufacturing workshop. His family shared an immense passion for football, spending weekends watching matches and engaging in the sport whenever possible.
莱昂内尔·安德烈斯·梅西出生于1987年6月24日，在一座充满足球氛围的城市长大，那就是圣菲省最大的城市罗萨里奥。梅西由父亲和母亲抚养长大。父亲是一家钢铁厂的经理，同时兼职担任足球教练；母亲则在一家磁铁制造工厂工作。他的家人都对足球怀有极大的热情，周末常常一起看比赛，并尽可能参与足球运动。
Well, Messi was born into a football family. His dad was a coach, and he was born in a football city. Rosario in Argentina was one of the host cities for the World Cup in 1978, almost ten years before Messi was born.
梅西出生在一个足球家庭。他的父亲是一名教练，而他出生的罗萨里奥也是一座足球城市。阿根廷的罗萨里奥曾是1978年世界杯的举办城市之一，那是在梅西出生前将近十年。
This is a city that loves the game, and it's a family that loves the game, that is steeped in the game through his father. And Lionel Messi, his first influence is through, of course, his father's love for football, but also his grandmother's willingness to take him anywhere that football takes him as he begins to make his way in the local football scene.
这是一座热爱足球的城市，也是一个热爱足球的家庭，而这种足球文化正是通过他的父亲深深影响着整个家庭。当然，梅西最初受到的影响来自父亲对足球的热爱，同时也来自祖母。她愿意带着他去任何足球能够带他去的地方，陪伴他一步步在当地足球圈崭露头角。
Messi quickly developed a passion for the sport as he was surrounded by it. He constantly played with his older brothers, Rodrigo and Matias, and by the age of four was determined to join a local team.
由于一直生活在足球环境中，梅西很快便爱上了这项运动。他经常和哥哥罗德里戈、马蒂亚斯一起踢球，并在四岁时便下定决心加入当地的一支球队。
His father, who is a coach, takes him to the local club, Grandoli, and looks after him there, and influences his first steps as a very young player, four years old when he goes to Grandoli.
他的父亲身为教练，把他带到了当地俱乐部格兰多利，在那里照顾他，并影响了他作为一名年仅四岁小球员的最初成长。
But of course, Newell's old boys are the Rosario club, and the club that Messi has supported all his life.
当然，纽维尔老男孩队是罗萨里奥最具代表性的俱乐部，也是梅西一生支持的球队。
And, you know, very quickly they become aware of any emerging talent on their doorstep, and little Lionel Messi is very much an emerging talent.
他们很快便注意到了家门口出现的新秀，而小梅西正是其中最耀眼的一位。
Messi moved clubs when he was six years old, joining the Newell's old boys, a local club located in Rosario.
梅西六岁时转会加盟了位于罗萨里奥的纽维尔老男孩队。
Here he played for over six years, developed his skills even more, garnering more match experience, and surrounded himself with other future prospect players.
在这里，他效力了六年多，不断提升自己的球技，积累了更多比赛经验，并与许多未来的新星共同成长。
Whilst at Newell's, Messi was already showing off what type of player he was going to become in the six years at the club.
效力纽维尔期间，梅西已经开始展现出他未来将成为怎样的一名球员。
He went on to score almost 500 goals, and became a member of the Machine of 87, who were named that due to the fact that they were the near unbeatable youth side since their birth in 1987.
此后，他一共打进了近500粒进球，并成为了"87机器队"的一员。这支球队因1987年出生、几乎所向披靡的青年队阵容而得名。
Audiences loved watching Messi play, as he was not only scoring regularly, he would also perform tricks at halftime.
观众都喜欢看梅西踢球，因为他不仅进球稳定，还会在中场休息时表演各种花式技巧。
It seemed like his career in football was going to blossom.
看起来，他的足球生涯即将迎来绽放。
But at the age of 11, Messi received some news that would put his professional football career at risk.
但就在11岁时，梅西得知了一个消息，这让他的职业足球生涯陷入了危险。
The problem for Lionel Messi is that it becomes apparent by the age of 11 that he's not really growing at all, and he's diagnosed with this growth hormone deficiency, which casts his whole future into doubt.
梅西面临的问题是，到11岁时，大家已经明显发现他几乎没有长高，随后他被诊断出患有生长激素缺乏症，这使他的整个未来都蒙上了阴影。
Spanish
他知道自己年纪还小，也知道自己在体育运动中处于劣势。很多孩子希望长高，是因为外貌、异性等原因；而他想长高，只是因为他想踢足球。他一直都说，自己一定会长大去踢足球，因为他真的热爱这项运动。He was aware that he was young, and that he was at a disadvantage in sports. When kids don't grow up, they're interested in being tall, because they want to be taller, because of their looks, because of the girls, because he wanted to play football. He always said that he was going to grow up to play football, because he wanted to play.
Messi underwent the treatment despite the fact that it cost his family almost $1,000 a month. He continued to play for Newell's, putting in great performances every week. But things were about to change for the young Lionel Messi.
尽管治疗每个月要花费家里近1000美元，梅西还是接受了治疗。他继续为纽维尔老男孩队效力，并且每周都有出色的表现。然而，年轻的梅西即将迎来人生的重要转折。
So Messi at this stage is still with Newell's, he's still trying to tackle this problem of will he grow enough to be a footballer. Some people say he's never going to amount to anything. River Plate are interested in signing him as well.
此时的梅西仍然效力于纽维尔老男孩队，仍在努力面对一个问题，那就是他是否能够长到足以成为一名职业足球运动员。有些人甚至认为他将来不会有什么出息。与此同时，河床队也有意签下他。
But the family looked beyond that. He has connections in Spain, in Catalonia, and he ends up at the age of 13 having a trial with Barcelona, and Barcelona immediately want to sign him.
但梅西一家看得更长远。他们在西班牙加泰罗尼亚有关系，因此梅西13岁时获得了在巴塞罗那试训的机会，而巴萨立刻就想签下他。
The Messi family travelled to Barcelona after receiving the go-ahead for the trial. Almost immediately during the trial, Barcelona's first team director, Carles Rexach, wanted to sign him as he saw an instant talent.
在获得试训许可后，梅西一家前往巴塞罗那。试训几乎一开始，一线队主管卡莱斯·雷克萨奇就看出了他的天赋，希望立刻签下他。
But unfortunately, due to his age and the fact he wasn't from Catalonia, the board of directors were hesitant to bring him in.
然而，由于他的年龄以及并非加泰罗尼亚本地人的身份，董事会对于引进他仍然有所犹豫。
If you try and imagine the 13-year-olds at a trial with Barcelona, these are not the ordinary kids that you and I play with on the street.
想象一下那些参加巴萨试训的13岁孩子，他们可不是你我平时在街头见到的普通孩子，
These are already the creme de la creme. But when Lionel Messi walks into this trial, nobody at Barcelona is under any illusions at all.
而都是最顶尖的佼佼者。但当梅西走进试训场时，巴萨内部没有任何人对他的实力抱有怀疑。
He is the cream of that already very, very exclusive club, and they have to have him.
即使是在这样一个精英云集的群体中，他也是最优秀的那一个，因此他们必须签下他。
A few months later, Barcelona were given the final chance to sign the Argentine prodigy, and on the 14th of December, Messi was offered his contract, which was written on a paper napkin.
几个月后，巴塞罗那迎来了签下这位阿根廷神童的最后机会。12月14日，梅西收到了一份写在纸餐巾上的合同。
Barcelona was his new home, and in February 2001, the Messi family relocated to an apartment in the city.
从此，巴塞罗那成为了他的新家。2001年2月，梅西一家搬进了城里的一套公寓。
Despite being signed to one of the biggest clubs in Europe, Messi was finding it hard to integrate into the youth squad due to the Spanish footballing law.
尽管加盟了欧洲最大的俱乐部之一，但由于西班牙足球相关规定，梅西很难融入青年队。
He was unable to play any games apart from friendlies and Catalan league games.
除了友谊赛和加泰罗尼亚联赛外，他无法参加任何正式比赛。
Because of this, his relationship with other teammates was almost non-existent, with some of them labeling him a meat.
因此，他几乎没有机会与队友建立关系，有些队友甚至把他当成局外人。
On top of that, his mother moved back to Rosario with his brothers and little sister, leaving him with just his father, causing him to feel constantly homesick.
此外，母亲带着哥哥和妹妹搬回了罗萨里奥，只留下他和父亲生活，这让他一直非常想家。
Eventually, in 2002, Messi was enrolled in the Royal Spanish Football Federation, meaning he was now eligible to play in all competitions.
最终，在2002年，梅西完成了西班牙皇家足协的注册，这意味着他终于有资格参加所有正式比赛。
He had also befriended some of his junior teammates. Those included Cesc Fabregas and Gerard Pique.
他也和几位青年队队友成为了朋友，其中包括法布雷加斯和皮克。
Now eligible to play in all competitions, Messi displayed his true talent to all the Barcelona staff, and that year Messi became part of the youth team known as the Baby Dream Team, Barcelona's greatest ever youth side.
如今终于获得所有赛事的参赛资格后，梅西向巴萨所有教练和工作人员展现了真正的天赋。同年，他成为了被称作"梦之少年队"的青年队成员，这也是巴萨历史上最出色的青年队之一。
During his first season in 2002-2003, Messi ended up the top scorer with 36 goals in just 30 games because of this phenomenal season for the Cadets.
2002至2003赛季，他在仅30场比赛中攻入36球，成为队内最佳射手。
Messi was getting recognized all over Europe in 2003.
凭借这个现象级赛季，梅西在2003年开始闻名整个欧洲。
He received an offer from Arsenal to join the team. But despite the fantastic offer, Messi decided he wanted to stay loyal to Barcelona.
阿森纳曾向他发出邀请，希望他加盟球队。但尽管条件十分诱人，梅西还是决定忠于巴塞罗那。
The 2003-2004 season became an iconic season for Lionel Messi.
2003至2004赛季也因此成为了他职业生涯中具有标志性意义的一个赛季。
Within this season, he flew up the ranks, debuting for a record five teams in a single campaign.
在这个赛季里，他一路飞速晋升，在同一个赛季中创纪录地先后代表五支球队完成首秀。
During this season, he played for the Juveniles B, Juveniles A, Barcelona C, and Barcelona B teams.
他先后效力于Juveniles B、Juveniles A、巴塞罗那C队以及巴塞罗那B队。
Before he'd even got into Barcelona's first team, all the first-teamers were aware of him.
甚至在进入巴萨一线队之前，所有一线队球员就已经知道梅西了。
There'd been this occasion where a lot of them were away on an international break, and so they needed players to come in and take part in first-team training, and Messi was one of those.
有一次，很多球员因为国际比赛日离队，所以球队需要青年队球员来参加一线队训练，而梅西就是其中之一。
And Ludovic Juli, the Barcelona French international player who was part of this training session, tells this story about how this little kid was absolutely destroying people.
参加那次训练的法国国脚久利后来回忆说，这个小家伙简直把所有人都踢得毫无还手之力。
And grown men were being embarrassed by this little 15, 16-year-old kid on the training pitch, and FrankRijkaard could not ignore him.
训练场上，一群成年职业球员竟然被这个十五六岁的孩子踢得十分狼狈，主教练 Rijkaard根本无法忽视他的表现。
And very, very quickly, the Barcelona first-team was saying, this boy has to be involved.
很快，整个巴萨一线队都认为，这个孩子必须进入球队。
And at that time, Ronaldinho was the man at Barcelona, and Ronaldinho saw Lionel Messi train, and he picked him out as being the next Ronaldinho,一眼就认定他会成为"下一个小罗"，
当时，小罗是巴萨的头号球星，他看过梅西训练后，
the next big thing for Barcelona, and was insisting, more or less, that Lionel Messi became part of the first-team scene at the club.
也就是巴萨未来最大的希望，并几乎一直坚持要求俱乐部把梅西提拔到一线队。
Although Messi didn't officially play for the team in this season, he did finish that campaign, having scored for four of his five teams with a total of 36 goals in all official competition. Going into the 2004-2005 season, Messi finally made his debut for the Barcelona first-team, coming onto the field in the 82nd minute.
尽管那个赛季梅西并未真正代表一线队正式比赛，但他仍然在效力过的五支球队中，有四支都取得了进球，总共在正式比赛中攻入36球。进入2004至2005赛季后，梅西终于迎来了巴萨一线队首秀，并在第82分钟替补登场。
So when he was 17 and three months old, Lionel Messi became the youngest ever player to play in Barcelona's first team, coming on as a substitute against Espanyol, and his first goal followed soon after. Also the youngest player ever to score a goal for Barcelona's first team against Alba Fete at the end of that season, which finished in 2005. So now Lionel Messi, at the insistence of his teammates, is in the Barcelona side. 17
岁零3个月时，梅西成为巴塞罗那历史上最年轻的一线队出场球员，在对阵西班牙人的比赛中替补登场。不久之后，他便打进了一线队首球，并在2005赛季结束前成为巴萨历史上最年轻的进球者。至此，在队友们的一再支持下，梅西正式站稳了一线队。
Messi clocked over 77 minutes in just nine matches for the Barcelona team during this season. He was also a regular player for the B team, and a key one as well. But by the end of the season, it was clear to both staff and fans that Messi was the next superstar in the making, and was going to become a key player in the 2005-2006 season and the 2005-2006 campaign.
这个赛季，梅西代表巴萨一线队在9场比赛中累计出场超过77分钟。他同时也是巴萨B队的常规主力和核心球员。赛季结束时，无论教练组还是球迷都已经意识到，梅西正成长为下一位超级巨星，并将在2005至2006赛季成为球队的重要成员。
Lionel Messi was a full-time first-team player. He had been fully promoted from the B team, and was training with the team on a daily basis. Within the first few games, Messi was blowing away fans on both sides of the stadiums.
梅西正式成为了一线队球员。他已经完全从B队升入一线队，并每天随队训练。仅仅几场比赛之后，他就让双方球迷都为之惊叹。
His skills were truly on show, and his abilities were becoming renowned everywhere he went.
他的球技得到了充分展现，无论走到哪里，他的能力都越来越享有盛名。
While still a teenager, the world is taking note of Messi and recognizing that he is one of the greatest players already in the game at this very tender age. What he has, I think, is this incredible low center of gravity, such acceleration, such tremendous pace, he can glide across the ground. But he's also got an incredible physical strength, which despite his size, you wouldn't imagine that he could be as strong as he is.
尽管还只是个少年，整个世界已经开始关注梅西，并意识到他在如此年幼的年纪就已经是足坛最伟大的球员之一。我认为，他拥有极低的重心、惊人的爆发力和速度，能够轻盈地掠过球场。此外，尽管身材并不高大，他却拥有令人难以置信的身体力量，强壮得超乎人们的想象。
But he is literally kicked from pillar to post game in, game out, and it doesn't seem to affect him. He just gets back onto his feet and dribbles around people again, and it never seems to knock him.
但他几乎每场比赛都会遭到对手不断侵犯，却似乎丝毫不受影响。他总是重新站起来，再次带球过人，这些打击从未真正击垮过他。
Here's the youngest. Oh, look at that! Poetic for Messi.
这是最年轻的那位。看看这一球！对梅西来说，简直就像诗一样美。
And it's that kind of persistence and incredible strength to go with the pace and skill, which signals him out at this age as being something really, really special.
正是这种坚持不懈的精神，以及与速度和技术相结合的惊人力量，让他在这样的年纪就显得与众不同，成为真正非凡的球员。
Messi was starring in some of the biggest games Barcelona played in this season. He played four games against the biggest rivals, Real Madrid in La Liga, and Chelsea in the semi-final of the Champions League. Together with players like Samuel Eto'o and Ronaldinho, Messi was easily becoming a key player for Barcelona and helped strengthen their attacking force.
那个赛季，梅西在巴塞罗那最重要的几场比赛中都发挥了关键作用。他在西甲四次对阵死敌皇家马德里，还参加了欧冠半决赛对阵切尔西的比赛。与埃托奥和罗纳尔迪尼奥等球员并肩作战时，梅西已经逐渐成长为巴萨的核心球员，并进一步增强了球队的进攻火力。
But unfortunately, near the end of the season, Messi suffered from a hamstring injury, which would put him out of the first team completely, meaning he would go on to miss the Champions League final against Arsenal in Paris. Messi was devastated by this so much that he didn't even celebrate their win, something that he later came to regret. After fully recovering going into the 2006-2007 season, Barcelona were gradually declining in La Liga and European tournaments.
然而，不幸的是，赛季末梅西遭遇了腿筋伤势，这使他彻底无缘一线队，也因此错过了在巴黎举行的欧冠决赛，对手正是阿森纳。梅西对此深受打击，甚至没有庆祝球队夺冠，这也是后来他一直感到遗憾的事情。完全康复后进入2006至2007赛季时，巴塞罗那在西甲和欧洲赛场上的表现开始逐渐下滑。
But this didn't stop Messi's performance and actually helped him to develop more as a player. And despite the poor Barcelona form, this was actually Messi's most groundbreaking season so far. During this season, he went on to score 17 goals in just 36 games across all competitions.
不过，这并没有影响梅西的表现，反而帮助他成长为更加成熟的球员。尽管巴萨整体状态不佳，这却成为了梅西迄今为止最具突破性的一个赛季。他在各项赛事36场比赛中攻入了17粒进球。
He also got his first hat-trick for the club, scoring against their closest rivals, Real Madrid, in the Clásico match. This hat-trick meant that Messi was the first person to score one in an El Clásico match in over 12 years.
他还完成了自己在俱乐部的第一个帽子戏法，而且是在国家德比中攻破死敌皇家马德里的球门。这也是12年来首次有人在国家德比中完成帽子戏法。
This is the game that is going to be remembered as the Lionel Messi match.
这场比赛将会作为"属于梅西的一战"而被人们铭记。
It was clear that Messi was becoming an extremely important asset for the club and was actually being compared to his fellow countryman and footballing legend, Diego Maradona. This comparison was made clear to fans in April 2007, when Messi went on to score what could only be described as a Maradona-esque goal against Getafe in the first leg of the Copa del Rey semi-finals.
很明显，梅西已经成为俱乐部极其重要的财富，人们也开始把他与自己的同胞、足球传奇马拉多纳相提并论。2007年4月，在国王杯半决赛首回合对阵赫塔菲时，梅西打进了一粒只能用"马拉多纳式"来形容的进球，这种比较也因此更加深入人心。
There probably isn't a football fan in the world that hasn't seen the Diego Maradona goal against England in the World Cup quarter-final of 1986 in Mexico when he runs from inside his own half of the field, pretty much through the whole England team and glides around Peter Shilton and tucks the ball into the back of the net. Absolutely certain that there's no Argentine who hasn't seen that goal a countless number of times and of course Lionel Messi would have grown up with that goal from the great Maradona. So then in the Copa del Rey against Getafe, Messi picks the ball up inside his own half of the field.
世界上恐怕没有哪个球迷没看过马拉多纳在1986年墨西哥世界杯四分之一决赛对阵英格兰时打进的那粒经典进球。他从本方半场开始带球，几乎过掉整支英格兰队，晃过门将彼得·希尔顿后将球送入网窝。我敢肯定，没有任何一个阿根廷人不是看着这粒进球长大的，梅西当然也不例外。所以，在国王杯对阵赫塔菲时，梅西也是从本方半场开始带球推进。
I wonder at what point he realises that he's almost scoring the exact same goal, because it is extraordinary. From almost the same area of the pitch, beating players in exactly the same way, finishing in virtually the same way, Lionel Messi replicates one of the greatest goals we've ever seen.
我很好奇，他究竟是在什么时候意识到，自己几乎是在复制那粒一模一样的进球，因为这一切实在太不可思议了。从几乎相同的位置启动，以几乎相同的方式过人，又以几乎相同的方式完成射门，梅西完美复制了足球史上最伟大的进球之一。
Oh, brilliant skill from Lionel Messi. Surging forward with real menace here. Brilliant from Messi.
梅西的技术太精彩了！他带着巨大的威胁一路向前推进。太精彩了，梅西！
Oh, what a goal that is!
这球太精彩了！
This goal sent shockwaves all over the world as it was not only a good goal, it was a world-class goal that could only be achieved by a few people. Messi was being regarded as the best player in the world and still at only the age of 19. With Ronaldinho out of the squad and the following season, he had become the star player for the squad.
这粒进球震惊了全世界，因为它不仅仅是一粒漂亮的进球，更是一粒只有极少数球员才能完成的世界级进球。当时年仅19岁的梅西，已经被认为是世界最佳球员。随着罗纳尔迪尼奥离开球队，在接下来的赛季中，梅西正式成为了球队的头号球星。
At the 2007 Ballon d'Or, Messi made the podium alongside Kaka and Cristiano Ronaldo. He unfortunately finished in the third spot, but it was still an incredible achievement for him. He also got nominated for FIFA World Player of the Year, coming second again behind Kaka, but beating Cristiano Ronaldo.
在2007年金球奖评选中，梅西与卡卡和克里斯蒂亚诺·罗纳尔多一同登上领奖台。虽然最终获得第三名，但这依然是一项了不起的成就。他还获得了国际足联世界足球先生提名，最终排名第二，仅次于卡卡，但领先于克里斯蒂亚诺·罗纳尔多。
I always said that I don't play to be the best in history, or the best of the moment, or anything like that. I play to try to do things right, first for the team, whether it's Barcelona or the Argentine national team, then for the people and, above all, for myself. It makes me feel good when things go my way, and that's how I live.
我一直都说，我踢球不是为了成为历史最佳，也不是为了成为当下最好的球员，或者其他类似的目标。我踢球只是想把事情做好，首先是为了球队，无论是巴塞罗那还是阿根廷国家队；然后是为了球迷；最重要的是，为了我自己。当事情朝着我希望的方向发展时，我会感到很开心，而这就是我的生活方式。
That's why I'm not afraid of what people say. I'm beyond all that, for the good, for the bad.
所以，我并不害怕别人怎么说。不管是赞扬还是批评，我都已经看淡了。
With Messi, Suárez and Neymar at the wheel, Barcelona were achieving record-breaking seasons. It seemed like the dependency on Messi was gone and they could all work together to win as many league titles as possible.
在梅西、苏亚雷斯和内马尔的带领下，巴塞罗那不断创造新的纪录。球队似乎已经不再依赖梅西一个人，而是能够共同协作，争取赢下尽可能多的联赛冠军。
Playing in the World Cup is different to everything else. To be able to play in the World Cup is something very nice. I think the best teams are there, and it's going to be very difficult for everyone.
世界杯和其他任何赛事都不同。能够参加世界杯本身就是一件非常美好的事情。我认为世界上最好的球队都会在那里，所以对每支球队来说都会非常困难。
I hope things go well for Argentina, and that we can achieve our objective. We're going to enjoy it. It's in South America, and we're going to be close to our fans.
我希望阿根廷一切顺利，希望我们能够实现目标。我们会享受这届世界杯。而且比赛在南美举行，我们能够离球迷更近。
I'm sure it's going to be great.
我相信这一定会是一届精彩的世界杯。
Whilst Messi's time at Barcelona seemed to be filled with record-breaking moments and constant league titles, his career playing for Argentina was telling a different story, one that was up for constant criticism.
尽管梅西在巴萨的生涯充满了打破纪录的时刻和接连不断的联赛冠军，但他在阿根廷国家队的经历却完全是另一番景象，一直饱受外界批评。
In contrast to his time at Barcelona, where silverware and trophies seemed to have come in a constant and steady flow, his career with Argentina has seen him finish runner-up so many times, Copa America, World Cup, it's almost been one disappointment after another.
与他在巴萨时期相比，那时冠军奖杯源源不断，而在阿根廷国家队，他却一次又一次屈居亚军，无论是美洲杯还是世界杯，几乎可以说是一场失望接着一场失望。
And somehow, Messi has never really stamped his personality on a World Cup finals.
不知为何，梅西始终没有真正在世界杯舞台上打下属于自己的烙印。
He did win the vote for the best player in the World Cup of 2014, but Argentina lost the final, of course, to Germany.
他确实获得了2014年世界杯最佳球员，但阿根廷最终还是输给了德国队。
And it felt like it was a consolation prize for Messi as an individual, because he deserves to be on that podium for what he's achieved throughout his career, whereas actually in that World Cup, was he the best player at the 2014 World Cup? Many people would say not.
这座奖项更像是给梅西个人的一份安慰奖，因为以他的整个职业生涯来看，他确实配得上站上领奖台。但如果只看那届世界杯，很多人并不认为他是表现最好的球员。
Again, a World Cup passing by without Messi being able to enlighten it in the way he has with his club.
又是一届世界杯过去了，梅西依然没能像在俱乐部那样点亮整个赛事。
Since playing for Argentina's first team, Messi had only gone on to get one World Cup grand final.
自从进入阿根廷国家队以来，梅西只打进过一次世界杯决赛。
And although he was the captain, the strength of the side always seemed to be questioned.
尽管他是队长，但这支球队的整体实力始终受到质疑。
Going into every international competition, despite having some of the best attacking players in the world.
每次参加国际大赛，尽管阿根廷拥有世界顶级攻击手，但外界依然对他们充满疑问。
You don't have to take all the responsibility, Leo, but we all have to try to contribute what each one knows, to try to achieve the goal that everyone already knows.
里奥，你不需要承担所有责任，但我们每个人都应该贡献自己所擅长的东西，共同去实现大家都知道的目标。
So, well, you have to be calm, you have to work a lot, all these weeks we have, so that when the ball starts rolling, that we have the first game, we try not to make mistakes.
所以，我们必须保持冷静，在比赛开始前努力训练，等到第一场比赛开打时，尽量避免犯错。
Probably one of the problems for Messi with Argentina is that it is all about Messi.
梅西在阿根廷面临的最大问题之一，就是所有事情都围绕着梅西展开。
And great though he is, Barcelona have always had fantastic players around him and behind him in Xavi and Iniesta or in Neymar and Suarez, whereas basically Argentina is Lionel Messi and has been for a long time.
尽管梅西非常伟大，但巴萨一直拥有哈维、伊涅斯塔、内马尔、苏亚雷斯这样的优秀队友，而阿根廷长期以来几乎只有梅西一个核心。
Despite the fact that there's Dybala and there's Aguero and other terrific players, if you stop Messi, you stop Barcelona, and that has counted against them.
尽管还有迪巴拉、阿圭罗等优秀球员，但只要限制住梅西，就等于限制住了阿根廷，而这一点始终对他们不利。
In 2016, after yet another disappointing display from Argentina at the world stage, Lionel Messi announced he was going to be retiring from international duty and not performing for Argentina in the next World Cup. 2016
年，在阿根廷又一次国际大赛表现令人失望之后，梅西宣布退出国家队，不再代表阿根廷参加下一届世界杯。
However, leading up to the 2018 World Cup, Messi found himself going back into training sessions and taking up the role of captain once again.
然而，在2018年世界杯前夕，梅西重新回到了训练场，再次担任队长。
Any footballer is going to look at their legacy in terms of titles won. And those include individual titles as well as club titles. So if you are to be considered as one of the best we've ever seen, you have to win the Ballon d'Or.
任何一位足球运动员都会用自己赢得的冠军来衡量自己的历史地位。这既包括个人荣誉，也包括俱乐部荣誉。因此，如果你想被认为是我们见过的最伟大的球员之一，就必须赢得金球奖。
You don't have to win it five times. But you might as well. Moving on to the 2016-17 UEFA Champions League, Barcelona went on to win one of the best comebacks ever seen before in Champions League history.
你当然不一定非得拿五次金球奖。不过，如果能做到，那自然再好不过。进入2016至2017赛季欧冠，巴塞罗那完成了欧冠历史上最伟大的逆转之一。
Barcelona beat Paris Saint-Germain 6-1 in the second leg, after losing nil in the first leg. MSN showed their true strength during this game, with Suarez opening the match with a goal within the first three minutes. Neymar scored two goals and Messi scored a penalty.
首回合0比4失利后，巴塞罗那在次回合6比1击败巴黎圣日耳曼。MSN组合在这场比赛中展现了真正的实力，苏亚雷斯开场三分钟内便率先破门，内马尔攻入两球，梅西则罚进一粒点球。
This game displayed their true skill as a squad, and despite losing out during the Champions League quarter-final to Juventus, that one game stood out as one of the best displays of Barcelona's strength and determination as a squad in 2017. Barcelona lost Neymar to PSG. It was the end of the MSN trio.
这场比赛充分展现了他们作为一支球队的真正实力。尽管后来在欧冠四分之一决赛中输给了尤文图斯，但这场比赛依然是2017年巴萨团队实力和斗志最经典的代表作之一。随后，内马尔转会巴黎圣日耳曼，MSN组合也就此画上句号。
But despite the recent loss of one of their strongest strikers, Barcelona still went on to win the 2017-18 LaLiga Championship, making this the 25th trophy.
尽管刚刚失去了最强前锋之一，巴塞罗那依然赢得了2017至2018赛季西甲冠军，这也是俱乐部历史上的第25座联赛冠军。
There's always talk of the fight for the Ballon d'Or. Right now you're the clear favourite.
人们总是在讨论金球奖之争，而现在你显然是最大的热门。
What importance do you give it? Well, I've said it many times, right? The truth is that my goal is not the individual awards, nor that one, nor the boot, nor any of them. Our goal is to win everything we play for. As I said before, thank God we're on the right track and I hope we finish in the best way possible.
你有多看重这项荣誉？我已经说过很多次了。说实话，我的目标从来不是个人奖项，不管是金球奖、金靴奖，还是其他任何奖项。我们的目标是赢下所有能够争夺的冠军。正如我之前所说，感谢上天，我们目前走在正确的道路上，希望最后能以最好的方式收官。
Messi's career at Barcelona continues to thrive. In the season of 2018-2019, Messi became the top scorer in Europe once again, earning him his sixth European Golden Shoe, an achievement that only he has achieved with Cristiano Ronaldo behind him with four.
梅西在巴萨的职业生涯依然蒸蒸日上。2018至2019赛季，他再次成为欧洲最佳射手，赢得了个人第六座欧洲金靴奖，这项成就至今只有他做到，而C罗则以四座位居其后。
I understand your pride as a father.
我能理解你作为父亲的自豪。
I'm excited, I'm excited to hear it. That's why we wanted to go a little further and that Thiago and Mateo were not only witnesses of this event, which has already been shown in the video, but that they were also the main protagonists, that they were the ones who delivered the ball to the scorer. So I ask Thiago and Mateo to join me on the stage.
我很激动，听到这些我真的很激动。所以，我们想把这个环节做得更特别一些，让蒂亚戈和马特奥不仅仅作为见证者出现在视频里，更成为真正的主角，由他们亲手把奖球交给这位最佳射手。因此，我邀请蒂亚戈和马特奥来到台上。
But I think it's got to be in a Barcelona shirt that you look back on Messi in the Champions League finals that he won with them, particularly probably the one at Wembley in 2011 against Manchester United, when he was the outstanding player on the pitch, as he so often is.
但我认为，当人们回顾梅西的职业生涯时，最难忘的仍然会是他身穿巴萨球衣征战欧冠决赛，尤其是2011年温布利对阵曼联那场比赛。当时，他和往常一样，是全场最出色的球员。
And Barcelona just toyed with United on what was a very, very long evening for Alex Ferguson's team. And Messi just conjured and created that moment.
巴萨几乎是在戏耍曼联，那对于弗格森的球队来说是一个无比漫长的夜晚。而梅西则创造了那个经典时刻。
He created and conducted what was a fantastic Barcelona display.
他主导并组织了巴萨那场精彩绝伦的比赛。
Lionel Messi is the best player Barcelona has ever had the pleasure to have in the squad. And despite having constant offers from other clubs around the world, he has always stayed loyal to the Barcelona squad and frequently calls it his home.
梅西是巴萨有幸拥有过的最伟大的球员。尽管世界各地的俱乐部不断向他发出邀请，但他始终忠于巴萨，并且经常把这里称作自己的家。
Barcelona and Messi have been together for so long now that it seems almost inconceivable that they could ever part.
巴萨和梅西已经携手走过太多年，以至于人们几乎无法想象双方有一天会分开。
It may happen, but I think the reason that he's always turned down approaches from any other club is partly if you go back to his childhood. He's from a family that has some roots in Catalonia.
当然，这种事也不是完全不可能发生。但我认为，他一直拒绝其他俱乐部邀请，部分原因要追溯到他的童年。他的家族与加泰罗尼亚有着一定的渊源。
He's very aware of what Barcelona did for him with his medical problems as a very young player.
他非常清楚，在自己年幼时遭遇健康问题时，是巴萨帮助了他。
He only really speaks Spanish, and he is very, very comfortable in the city and the environment of Barcelona, who have given him everything he could ever want in terms of trophies and success, working under the lights of Guardiola, winning just about everything there is to win. Barcelona have given him all of that.
他主要使用西班牙语，也早已习惯了巴塞罗那这座城市和这里的生活环境。巴萨给予了他所有他梦寐以求的东西，包括冠军、成功，以及在瓜迪奥拉麾下赢得几乎所有能够赢得的荣誉。这一切，都是巴萨给予他的。
There have been no disappointments in his club career. All the disappointments have been with Argentina and his international career. So I think it would be a tremendous wrench for Messi to walk out on Barcelona.
他的俱乐部生涯几乎没有留下遗憾。所有遗憾，都来自阿根廷国家队。因此，我认为，对梅西来说，离开巴萨将会是一件极其痛苦的事情。
At the age of 32, Messi is still regarded as one of the best players to have ever graced the sport. He is still breaking records and still putting in monumental performances week in, week out at Barcelona. 32
岁的梅西依然被认为是足球历史上最伟大的球员之一。他仍不断打破纪录，并且每个星期都在巴萨奉献现象级表现。
In December 2019, Lionel Messi once again shattered another world record, as he went on to win his sixth Ballon d'Or trophy, beating Liverpool's Virgil van Dijk and Juventus' Cristiano Ronaldo for the title of the world's greatest player. 2019
年12月，梅西再次打破纪录，赢得个人第六座金球奖，击败了利物浦的范戴克和尤文图斯的C罗，再次当选世界最佳球员。
The sixth win pushed him ahead of Ronaldo and made him the only player to receive six Ballon d'Or trophies in the history of football.
第六次获奖使他超越了C罗，成为足球历史上第一位赢得六座金球奖的球员。
I think many people thought we'd never see anybody like Diego Maradona, and out of the same country came Lionel Messi, and has done everything that Maradona did, and has done more in terms of club success.
很多人曾认为，我们再也不会看到像马拉多纳那样的球员了。然而，同样来自阿根廷的梅西不仅做到了马拉多纳做到的一切，而且在俱乐部成就方面甚至更进一步。
And I think to be able to do it for a decade and a half, being kicked week in, week out, is something that even Maradona's body couldn't stand up to.
而且，能够在十五年的时间里，每周都遭受对手的严密侵犯，却依然保持这样的水平，我认为就连马拉多纳的身体也未必能够承受。
And Messi has done that. It's the sheer consistency, the incredible numbers of goals every season, not just a season now and again, but every season, which actually has to probably put Messi even above Maradona. And that is really saying something.
而梅西真的做到了。真正让他超越马拉多纳的，是他惊人的稳定性，是他每一个赛季都能交出不可思议的进球数据，而不是偶尔一个赛季爆发。这一点，足以说明一切。
But although he is known for his skills on the pitch, he is also known for his brand deals. Since 2006, Messi has had an ongoing partnership with Adidas, supplying him with boots and clothing.
不过，除了球场上的技术，梅西还因商业合作而广为人知。自2006年以来，他一直与阿迪达斯保持长期合作，由后者为他提供球鞋和服装。
In 2017, the brand took this relationship a step further, pushing forward a lifetime sponsorship deal with him to this date. 2017
年，阿迪达斯进一步深化双方合作，与他签下了一份终身赞助合同，并一直持续至今。
He is frequently promoting their merchandise and hosting their events.
他经常为品牌推广商品，并出席他们举办的活动。
Today we present your new boots. I wanted to ask, what do you value the most when it comes to changing boots? What undisputable conditions do you need to have to feel comfortable?
今天我们发布了你的新球鞋。我想问一下，在更换球鞋时，你最看重什么？有哪些不可妥协的条件，才能让你穿得舒服？
That they don't change as much as the previous ones, that they are more or less similar to what I have been using previously, because of the comfort issue.
我希望它们不要和以前的球鞋变化太大，最好和我之前穿的差不多，主要还是因为舒适度。
I think that for us, the fundamental thing is to feel good with what we use, to feel comfortable. Sometimes what the boots do, they look for a lot of differences, a lot of things to make the boots more visible, but what we want is comfort when we play, nothing more.
我认为，对我们来说，最重要的是穿着舒服。有时候品牌会追求很多创新，让球鞋更吸引眼球，但对于我们而言，比赛时最重要的还是舒适，仅此而已。
And do you participate in the design process of your own footwear, in addition to the technical issues of the boots? The truth is that yes, because as I just said, I do what I want and I would always like to be comfortable with what I use, and that's why I get involved in what they do, to try to do it together as best as possible.
除了球鞋的技术性能之外，你也会参与自己球鞋的设计吗？确实会。正如我刚才所说，我希望使用自己真正喜欢、真正舒服的装备，所以我会参与他们的设计过程，希望大家一起把产品做到最好。
Alongside that, he has also worked with brands such as Pepsi and EA Sports, having his face on the front of their products and having him star in their commercials.
除此之外，他还与百事可乐和EA Sports等品牌合作，他的形象被印在产品包装上，并主演他们的广告。
But in 2019, he also opened up his own clothing brand.
不过在2019年，他还创立了自己的服装品牌。
The store known as The Messi Store sells branded clothing, and more recently releasing his own hydration beverage.
这家名为"The Messi Store"的商店销售品牌服饰，最近还推出了自己的补水饮料。
Because of these intelligent business deals, Messi has now become the second wealthiest football player in the world, just behind Cristiano Ronaldo.
凭借这些高明的商业合作，梅西如今已经成为全球第二富有的足球运动员，仅次于C罗。
But Messi is also known for more than just his brand deals.
不过，梅西出名的不仅仅是他的商业合作。
He also does a lot of work for charities and has set up his own foundation called the Leo Messi Foundation, which has helped support children from less fortunate backgrounds, children with cancer and children with life-changing disabilities.
他还积极投身慈善事业，并成立了自己的公益基金会"里奥·梅西基金会"，帮助来自贫困家庭的儿童、患癌儿童以及身患严重残疾的儿童。
In July 2023, Messi joined Inter Miami CF in Major League Soccer, signing a contract that extends until December 31, 2025. 2023
年7月，梅西加盟美国职业足球大联盟的迈阿密国际，并签下了一份持续到2025年12月31日的合同。
As of now, there is no official confirmation regarding his retirement plans.
截至目前，关于他的退役计划仍没有官方确认。
Speculation exists about his future post 2025, with some suggesting he might retire after the 2026 World Cup.
关于他2025年之后的未来仍有许多猜测，有人认为他可能会在2026年世界杯后退役。
It's safe to say that he has inspired millions all over the world.
可以毫不夸张地说，他激励了全世界数以百万计的人。
And although he is one of the quietest and reserved players in the sport, everyone knows the name Lionel Messi because of his incredible performances on the pitch and his community work off the pitch.
虽然他是足坛最低调、最内敛的球员之一，但每个人都知道莱昂内尔·梅西这个名字，因为他在球场上的精彩表现，以及球场之外的公益贡献。
A whole generation of kids, boys and girls, have been absolutely inspired by Lionel Messi to play the game and to pretend to be Messi in the back garden, in the streets, in the yard.
整整一代孩子，无论男孩还是女孩，都因梅西而爱上足球，在后院、街头和院子里模仿他踢球。
And that's probably his legacy around the world.
这大概就是他留给全世界最重要的遗产。
I think his legacy in Argentina is probably quite a burden for him to bear because for all that he's done, he's done it in Europe, he hasn't really done it with a national team, they haven't won a World Cup or a Cup of America while he's been a part of that squad.
但我认为，在阿根廷，他留下的"历史地位"反而是一种沉重的负担。因为无论他取得了多少成就，几乎都是在欧洲完成的，而国家队始终没有在他效力期间赢得世界杯或美洲杯。
So while he's satisfied the world, perhaps back in Argentina, they're still hungry for the next Messi who can do even more.
所以，尽管他已经满足了全世界球迷的期待，但在阿根廷，人们或许仍然期待着下一个能够创造更多辉煌的"梅西"。
Messi's legacy will live on for years to come.
梅西的传奇将在未来很多年继续流传。
And although he is approaching retirement age, his ability is still at a world standard.
尽管他已经接近退役年龄，但他的竞技水平依然处于世界顶级。
He is the captain of Barcelona and one of the most idolized players of all time.
他是巴塞罗那的队长，也是足球历史上最受崇拜的球员之一。
No matter how long he keeps playing for, he will always be remembered as one of the greatest players of all time.
无论他还会踢多久，他都会被铭记为足球史上最伟大的球员之一。
Well, it's really difficult to imagine that there's anything about Lionel Messi's life in Barcelona and with Barcelona Football Club that isn't very nice indeed.
很难想象，梅西在巴塞罗那、以及在巴萨俱乐部的生活中，还有什么是不美好的。
However, he's never played in his native Argentina, he's never played a senior game in that country.
然而，他从未在自己的祖国阿根廷踢过职业一线队比赛。
It may be that he goes back to Rosario and decides he wants to play for Newell's Old Boys, the club he supported, in the way that Diego Maradona was always linked with Boca Juniors and couldn't resist going back then.
也许有一天，他会回到罗萨里奥，为自己从小支持的纽维尔老男孩队效力，就像马拉多纳始终与博卡青年联系在一起，最终也无法抗拒回归一样。
It may be that Messi decides that he does want to go back and play for his public, in his city, with his club.
也许梅西终究会决定回到自己的城市，为支持自己的球迷、自己的俱乐部而战。
Lionel Messi's name will forever be etched in football's history books.
莱昂内尔·梅西的名字将永远镌刻在足球史册之中。
A magician on the pitch, an inspiration off it, his legacy is immortal.
球场上，他是一位魔术师；球场外，他是一位激励无数人的榜样。他的传奇将永垂不朽。
I tried to keep everything that I learned from when I started in the first team until today.
我一直努力保留自己从进入一线队至今所学到的一切。
I tried to keep growing, as I always said, in the stage Guardiola was in, beyond the titles he won, which is always the most important thing.
正如我一直说的那样，我始终努力不断成长。尤其是在瓜迪奥拉执教时期，除了赢得冠军之外，我还学到了更多东西。当然，冠军始终是最重要的。
In the end, as a player, I grew and learned a lot and now I try to keep adding things to my football.
归根结底，作为一名球员，我成长了很多，也学到了很多。如今，我仍然努力不断丰富自己的足球。